all right welcome to the fourth fourth
of four idea cafe is on this same
question which is what are your thoughts
/ feelings on communism / Marxism so
because there's three of us I will also
participate just like we're just made in
the last three and so everybody can have
a chance to speak for up to five minutes
I will mute everyone else who isn't
speaking so you can talk and interrupt
it so would anyone like to remember what
I say from one to the other it's great
entry it's fresh every time would either
of you like to go I can also start if
I'm have practice this let's go you go
Eric okay all right well I mean first of
all this is not really a hot-button
topic for me it's not something I have
strong emotional attachment to either
way aye sir and equally I don't have any
deep learning or whatever on the topic
either so I speak very much as a lay
person on the subject my the the quote
that's often associated with Marxism the
idea of from each according to their
needs
- sorry from each according to their
abilities sorry to each according to
their needs that is an axiom which I
don't think many reasonable people would
actually disagree with and so the
implementation I accept has been to
understate a bit problematic over the
over the last century or so right the
attempts at the attempts of actual
implementation but and I know Jordan
Peterson gives this whole argument a
really bad rap that that wasn't real
Marxism but I but I think there is some
I think there was a good deal of truth
in that argument that it wasn't real
Marxism I can't believe that Marx if he
looked at that would think yeah that's
what I had in mind I just I don't I just
I can't believe that so yeah that's
really I think all I have to say on the
subject I will if I if I was to go on I
would really just I think repeat that
basic thing so that's that's really I
think all I have to say there's no need
to me to take up any more time
thank you would you like to go Brent or
would you like me to go you go ahead all
right my ideas on Marxism and communism
is ironically I haven't read a lot of
the actual literature I've watched a ton
of YouTube contents and videos because
that's what can now go into my brain
more so than the written word but I
understand I mean I learned about it in
school and I believe in a lot of the
principles I think there's a reason it
has stuck around in an ideology that
people love the the beauty of it but in
order to honor that you also have to
honor that when it's been implemented
it's been implemented with a lot of
violence and horrific outcomes and you
can't ignore that at the same time I
think people attribute a lot of death to
communism and they don't attribute death
to capitalism and capitalism for me is a
much more hot-button topic the issue is
we're all in it for the fish and water
so we don't attribute all of the deaths
from cancer all of the deaths from not
having access to medical care all the
deaths from having non proper nutrition
and and like we just don't attribute
those to capitalism even if they are
directly related to somebody seeking
profit over help you know common humans
hope I don't you man's their their
common fellow humans and so I think a
lot I've been talking for years before
even finding a game be about dismantling
capitalism which was essentially
creating game be out of from great game
a and when everyone here is that they're
like that you must be a communist you
must be a socialist might be trying must
be trying to recreate communism and to a
degree I am I'm trying to create a
common technology that is safe enough to
try that isn't ever forced and so that
to me I can see the downfalls in the
systems that have come before and the
positives and I seek to create something
that harnesses the positives without the
negatives which means you always have to
be open for what is failing and what is
not working and seek truth over what I
want or we want to be the truth that
like it just isn't implemented right
it's like well is it being implemented
what are we learning and how can we how
can we improve it and so that is
my answer to that question today at 2:00
p.m. okay my turn my life mm-hmm yeah
I'm on the same page as both of you so
this isn't gonna be that difficult I'm
glad there's not lots of people but mmm
for me what it comes down to is just the
the culture war largely has this
aversion to the word Marxism and Marxism
and communism are different things and
there's different types of Marxism right
so it's not a monolith and you both
admit to some extent that you're not
fully versed in it I'm reluctant to say
I'm versed in it too but but my
background is sociology and so so
Marxism as a critical approach is
actually a foundational kind of
cornerstone of sociology like you can't
really do it do it without Marxism there
are other approaches and there's there's
anti-marxist sociologists but but it's
part of the discourse right so so people
should appreciate that so it shouldn't
be a scare a scare word right because
there's lots you can look into about
Marxism not as an ideology but as an
academic kind of approach and critique
that actually dissolves a lot of these
misunderstandings in tensions above the
terms and between capitalism and
socialism and there are there are
numbers it's probably debatable but
there are numbers on the death toll of
capitalism too right because there is
there is a kind of death toll it's just
not as direct or or a kind of concrete
as other forms of genocide or
annihilation um but it does add up and
it and it is comparable so mm-hmm you
know whatever label we we slap on the
system there's something else going on
sociologically like-likes okay like
there's no there's no pure communism
there's no pure capitalism or whatever
there's there's mixtures of all these
things and they and they co-opt each
other right in order to represent
themselves to something else so so Nazi
Germany was called socialist but it
wasn't socialist and in any coherent way
right it's just it's just a label and
there's just you know that this is only
a hot-button issue for me insofar as
it's a major dogma of kind of fans of
the intellectual dark web to be a
anti-marxist right to dismiss the
concept to say Marxism killed so many
people and it's been tried and failed
hmm it's just a straw man really in to
some extent a dog whistle too because it
detracts from like the the kind of
seriousness of the discourse of Marxism
which is about a class analysis of
alienation about capital the way capital
works so as I said I'm not I'm not an
expert but I feel like I could talk
about this Burnett for an hour because
there is a lot of depth there right
there's publications like Jacobin which
are explicitly marxist
that's that's their kind of program and
and it's worth it's worth reading right
it's not worth dismissing so so when it
comes to game B the issue is not Oh
Marxism is game a or a game be like
clearly capitalism is kind of game a but
Marxism as a kind of critical approach
has you know historical components that
we could consider part of game a like
obviously failed communism as part of
game a but but the idea maybe ideas the
more abstract ideas behind Marxism of
historical materialism of evolution
planetary evolution of kind of metabolic
rift rifts in ecology at nakhon economy
these are these are kind of concepts
that that take us from game a to game B
ostensibly so so it's it's a discourse
and the
Marxism as a as a tool kit helps us get
there helps us cross over into a new
paradigm that's actually kind of part of
the part of the premise of original
Marxism is that mmm history is this
long-term
struggle that plays out through
dialectic and that in the end whether
that end is you know 25 years after when
Marx was writing or 200 years after Marx
was writing that on the on the macro
scale globalization is actually a
evolutionary process and it's unfolding
in a certain direction there's a certain
teleology behind it so there's a huge
difference between um kind of picking up
on that as like a prescription for what
we should do and just a description of
what's happening so that in itself kind
of reinforces agency and structured
debates but but we can't we can't escape
trying to address address this
globalization question and and to
analyze it properly you need to keep
Marxism in the discourse so to speak hmm
so one thing that comes up in game B
sometimes is Robert Wright's book
nonzero and I wouldn't say that that's
that's Marxist but but it it it
dovetails with what I'm talking about
of kind of a lot a long term
evolutionary approach that posits the
kind of convergence of human societies
and a kind of a synthesis of differences
but but with with the economic
inequality in class struggle today of
course and the financial crisis a decade
ago like the the topic of Menem of of
Marxism is very salient like it's it's
very important it shouldn't be dismissed
by people who could you know take a kind
of straw man version of it I think I
think we're all in the same page with
that homie I think I think absolutely to
get behind that yeah I mean it's
actually what put me off - and Peterson
in the end was this ridiculous lying
spot he has you know what I mean that
anything socialist is a one way to get
to the GU legs you know it's it's it's
just for someone who sells themselves as
being
all about peeling back you know what I
mean layers of obscurity to get to the
truth is his his live dismissal of
Marxism I just thought it doesn't fit
it's always really bothered me about him
because I followed him for a while I
mean I was really really into him for a
while for a few months I was you know
absorbing everything I could have his
and but but more and more and more that
persistent message really started I even
made a video about it no one ever
watched it but I even made a you said
there Brent and in a way just restate
them but just just for that just for the
sake of clarity because I mean I think I
agree with what you were saying that
Marx is not really a prescription for
how to run the world more it's an
analysis of what has gone before what
its failings are you know what I mean
it's a it's a tool for critiquing it's a
lens through which to view things it's
not a prescription of how to do things
yes it is that essentially what you were
saying yeah no doubt there's factions
that take it more seriously as a
prescription like if you're if you're
Jacobean or if you're into labor and
union organizing you know you're you're
doing the type of praxis right so you're
putting that knowledge into action yeah
so that's definitely a part of it the
question is like like like to what
extent is it healthy is it is it true is
it viable right these are these are the
more practical questions but but as a
discourse it's there's such a complex
history there's there's dozens and
dozens of very famous Marxist thinkers
right like like Frantz Fanon or or Louie
althrough say and hmm you know or a more
more contemporary thinkers like like
Deleuze and jiseok to various extents
like there's there's a lot of depth and
complexity here one of my favorite kind
of approaches is uh what's-his-name
mm-hmm
forget his name but he wrote Marxist
ecology Marx Marx is ecology John
Bellamy Foster is his name
other contemporary thinkers like Marxist
economists like David Harvey and Richard
wolf like these are the experts these
are the people that I would defer to and
understand how to you know keep
exploring the ideas of and and also
exploring the Praxis but Richard Wolfe
has been getting some traction on the
internet he's got a lot of followers on
the interim it's definite as you've
already said it's it's salient now right
it's been picking up a lot of young
people who are interested you know what
I mean they want to learn more about it
and people like Richard Wolford I think
yeah I really I'm a big fan of his it's
the only one I know out of all of those
names you tube channel because I
disagree that I don't think that worker
cooperatives are solution for the future
this was not very Omega of me but it's
rivalries isn't it that workers unions
thing is rivalries it's it's workers
versus management rather than start
figuring out some way to collaborate and
you know share a vision of where we all
want to go together its its its rival
risks then yeah for that reason I don't
like it is not gonna be I mean I think
if we had implemented it two or three
decades ago awesome but I'd like the
time it would take to implement that and
then there's not real I'm like it
doesn't deal with any of the actual
economy issues like what about the
rivalry between the worker cooperatives
and how do you how do you compete on a
global scale and how do you do you do
any of that but I do like but did he I
just watch me because I was when you in
to mention that Marxism is different
than communism I was like I'm gonna need
a refresher course and so I was just
watching this 10-minute spiel on on the
difference between them and how Marxism
is everywhere and that he's like you
know that management doesn't take into
consideration the worker which is like
the biggest body that's involved and I'm
like what about the user the consumer
they're a bigger number
is involved and to me a consumer
cooperative has more power because where
we buy things for more places than we
work we work one place maybe and I would
like to work no place like I would like
to not have labor or be the center of my
life or other people's lives but but I
do find him very brilliant I just don't
agree with his take on how we actually
solve things
yeah I think like I think to be like
like to try to fulfill some kind of pure
Marxists economic program like maybe
maybe wolf is is doing might you know
might be a bit dysfunctional in
different ways so I don't completely
subscribe you know to everything he says
in particular but I I mean I go back to
my core point like it's such an
essential part of sociology as a
discipline like how can you study
society without understanding the
richness of these khans these concepts
and right and why why Marx and Marxism
is regarded as a kind of important
intellectual legacy and this there's a
there's a broader point here as well
isn't there that it's the difference
between ideologies and ideas right that
you know if you label yourself a Marxist
then you have to agree with everything
that there is in that doctrine Ryan
anything that contradicts it you also
mentioned you can't agree with and so
it's the ability to say yeah that's good
about that but that's not good about
that and that's good about this or even
though it's a completely contradictory
you know set of philosophies in many
ways but actually there is some
synthesis to be made between this
element of this and this element of this
that would work really well and so it's
the it's having the intellectual freedom
to be able to do that right to drop
ideas when actually okay this works best
than that and just just that's it just
drop it
you know the people don't do that they
hang on and this is what I mean about
the differences and ideas right ideology
is when it's stuck and it's become a
part of your identity it's not just it's
not just a tool that you hang on to
until it's not useful anymore it's
actually integrated into into your
identity so that I think this is why
this becomes such a hot-button issue for
things like jordan peterson fans right
because they feel so much gratitude and
loyalty to him for you know whatever
he's done for them in terms of waking
them up and helping them find richness
and meaning and paths to go down in
their lives and I think he has genuinely
helped a lot of people in that kind of
regard and so when he gets on this thing
about marx's and they have to in a way
jump on board with that because they're
in their own way ideologically possessed
by jordan peterson who preaches against
the ideological possession
yeah absolutely
and that was part of what the richard
wolf thing when i talked about and I had
made a note of it as well that like if
you're attributing Marx's ideas to
communism and therefore all of the
deaths from communism to Marxism that
you kind of also need to do that with
Christianity right that like Jesus is
what Jesus spoke about if you believe
that that was a real person was
beautiful like who disagrees with what
Jesus said but the Crusades all of these
things that happen in order to push
forth that ideology is horrific and yet
no one in the West even people who are
atheist or like well we're gonna
attribute one to the other right if
you're if you're Christian you were for
the Crusades and that's the and the
other one I have down here is Darwin and
evolution like this idea that because
someone came up with an idea that
they're the like gospel truth when they
don't have today's understanding I mean
Marx died over a hundred years ago
Darwin died you know around that that
long ago and they didn't have the
internet they didn't have globalization
they didn't have these things that we
have now how could they possibly foresee
for see into the future what what these
things are and so we have to be able to
take it and apply it which means not
treating it as gospel yeah and you know
Peterson refused to debate Richard
Wolffe and you know I'm not you know
there's no guarantees that would have
been interesting or or fruitful anyways
but Peterson did debate jus Jack and
that was very telling that was a kind of
watershed moment for
people because yeah what you were saying
Eric about how you were you know kind of
a fan of Peterson for a long time and
then your your interest waned as these
kind of red flags came up I mean this is
something interest very interesting to
me because from the very beginning uh I
felt like I could recognize what
Peterson was right about and what he was
interesting about and the things he was
flat wrong about and the kind of
pathological aggression towards people
he doesn't like like Foucault right when
you know yeah yeah whatever like he just
goes to town on these people like like
short of calling them fascists he says
they're the kind of most reprehensible
dangerous people in the 20th century
like like hyperbole would be an
understatement
in that case right but it's you know
these things were obvious to me because
Peterson's just so anti sociological
like I just on the face of it um but but
it's taken people so long to kind of
catch up to that because he is so
personal persuasive and he is so kind of
well-read in his own areas of expertise
um and you don't you don't have to like
be a super fan of Foucault but like it's
just like with Marx like you can
recognize his place in intellectual
history and you know and respect that
path it's the same thing with with
Chomsky like like Chomsky debated
Foucault they're able to respect each
other and appreciate each other to some
extent and then Sam Harris debates Noam
Chomsky and it's like totally
disrespectful it's it's definitely not
following um
kind of role alpha or whatever like it's
just projecting on to Chomsky and it's
you know yeah it's very kind of
unprofessional adolescent and you'd
expect more from something like Sam
Harris where Jordan Peterson for that
matter yeah I mean there's another thing
that happens after period so I'm I think
Sam Harris is a really good example of
this he sold a lot of books he's got a
lot of subscribers on his channel
lots of patreon contributors all of this
kind
malarkey and so he's kind of fenced
himself into a particular position right
you know he can't he can only really
talk about things from you know even if
he was to suddenly change his mind
dramatically about something profound
and important he couldn't really say so
because that's it that's that is that's
his living gone you know what I mean and
so it's a real danger of becoming
popular is that you you it traps you
into continuing to be what you've been
before it stops you from evolving so
it's another thing I wanted to I wanted
to mention to you on this mention that's
can't remember where I heard this but I
thought it was a really interesting idea
and it fits into the sort of Peterson
being the antithesis of and so someone
said to me that Peterson's wisdom if you
want to call it that comes from the fact
that he has obviously at some point
looked into the abyss right and had to
deal with that right whereas the wisdom
of someone like Charles Eisenstein for
example who I really like I'm a big fan
of his is the exact opposite his is sort
of taking an aerial view and looking
from you know looking from a high place
you know what could be a zit and so that
but there's but but both of these
aspects of wisdom are actually important
you know what I mean you do have to have
looked into the abyss but at the same
time you have to have experienced the
Bliss of the of the you know the eagle
flying high sort of thing you know and I
I thought that was a really interesting
idea of bottom-up and top-down kind of
wisdom grounded and idealistic or if you
like that sort of thing what do you
think of that idea do you like that uh
yeah another another thought that just
occurred to me it's sort of tangential
but coming back to this idea of
alienation just because Peter Peterson
talks about alienation somewhat so it's
ironic when somebody talks about a topic
like like that but they don't they don't
realize how integral it is to Marxism
right so he can't then take on a Marxist
perspective of alienation but but but
more specifically about what you're
saying like I find it interesting
because I feel like I've done both or at
least I've tried to do both I've stared
into the
this and I've taken the kind of overview
approach kind of looking at big systems
and whatever your you're getting out
with Eisenstein there like I appreciate
appreciate that approach to but it's
interesting because Peterson stares into
the abyss and I stared with the abyss
and we see different things Peterson has
this very very well-defined kind of
upbringing like like like everyone knows
his bio more or less like he's from
northern Alberta he's like raised like
kind of conservative religious but also
had like a socialist streak in in his
use in his life and then had whatever
epiphany that that was wrong and I mean
this is another point that's been kind
of challenged or debunked by Nathan
Robinson bet that Peterson's reasons for
abandoning socialism were pretty
misinformed like he misread Orwell
thinking that Orwell was actually
against socialism when when in reality
Orwell is like critical by at heart a
socialist hmm so this uh yeah this idea
of staring into the abyss we need to
disentangle it from the the
judeo-christian worldview that that
Peterson thinks is is reality well it's
like it's just it's just a relative
everywhere right it's not just it's not
just it's not just Christianity is
everywhere but I think that's universe
Joseph Kennedy as part of the hero's
journey as well isn't it that they're
staring into the abyss and and and and
you know in that finding the strength to
then you know to face the dragon but
yeah sorry I've lost stuff completely
off so I was gonna say what everyone's
gone well we're coming up to the
half-an-hour remark that's how the idea
cafes are designed to be around half an
hour so we can have closing statements
and then go unlive and discuss what we
want to do with this recording as well
as continue the conversation if we want
the extended version that won't be
published
it's pretty much have a like a brief
wrap-up of their thoughts I would just
add a few things that I that I didn't
mention like like one of my main sources
for news and political commentaries the
Michael Brooks show and he describes
himself sometimes as an integral Marxist
because he has a background in both and
just that that you know his his his
platform his guests and the kind of
leftist culture that's emerging there is
very healthy I think like it it deserves
attention and credit and just I have
queued up here some podcasts from from
yesterday revolutionary left radio is a
is a great source like there's there's
tons of great content out there that
addresses a lot of these topics and in
issues that have been dominated by IDW
thinking over the past couple years and
it's just it's uh it's I think it's the
time to like explore collectively this
this discourse you know explore the
toolkit like think about it critically
not throw the baby out with the
bathwater yeah I would agree give any
closing thoughts Eric not at all
contentious right we're all clearly very
much broadly in agreement here right so
there's yeah there's really not been
there's not been that I mean though the
thought which is never it's obvious when
you say it but it never occurred to me
was the idea that you know it's very
easy to say that whatever 30 million
died in the gulags and 20 million died
in the Holocaust and whatever the
numbers are but it's it's never talked
about what is it the step I'm pretty
sure this is a UN stat it is from a few
years ago but I'd see no reason to think
it would have changed nationally there
were a hundred thousand people every
single day died in the world right now
due to malnutrition and preventable
disease right so essentially they're
dying because they don't have enough
money to buy the food and the medicines
which exist in plentiful supply in the
world right and so you know that's that
source of structural violence for which
capitalism is directly
responsible you know that's a hundred
thousand people a day what's that that's
that's that's 35 million people a year
you know every single year in year in
year out factory soil you know what I
mean so yeah and the the fact that that
is never talks about that all reckoned
if you like in the tally of deaths when
when you look at the two systems versus
each other I think that's a really
interesting point as I said obvious when
you say it but I never really thought of
it before
mmm-hmm I think about those things all
the time it's I'm gonna go back and
watch this and look up some of the the
people you've mentioned grunts
especially the last one because integral
meets Marxism sounds like my kind of
thing to listen to putting in new
information I don't feel the needs like
go out and learn external knowledge I
want to look interior like I feel like
I've done enough of that and it's more
but then the odd time something comes up
and like yes that that I do want to add
I don't want to continually be looking
for new knowledge and not using the
knowledge I have just have an actual
difference in the world
but I also want to be open to to
learning new things so I will stop
recording and then we can go on live by
YouTube